OK, we are going to continue our scaling journey.
Today's a bit of a grab bag of stuff.
I mean, we're really going to talk about some
of the more advanced details of scaling laws
and how we scale up models.
And in doing so, we're going to cover
what I feel like are some important details in how
you would scale up a language model in practice.
So we might want to ask some questions, like the scaling law
stuff that you talked about two lectures ago,
does that actually work at real building open-source model
scales?
It would be nice if we could optimize some of this.
There's a lot of learning rate tricks and other things
that people do that I think you should know
as people that are informed about how
to build language models.
So we'll talk about some of these optimization details.
And then I think the last thing I want to talk about
is, when we scale up, there are certain things that
are going to be a little bit trickier to tune.
We know that optimizers and optimizer behavior
is going to be actually pretty scale sensitive.
And because of that, things like initializations,
learning rates, batch size, those
we need to carefully think about as a function of scale.
So we will talk about how to think about those carefully.
So up until now, most of our discussions
is what I would call the classical scaling laws cannon.
We talked about Kaplan.
We talked about, oh, even Hestness and then the Chinchilla
paper.
So we're up to date with, I don't know, 2022 or something.
Since then, there have been a number
of scaling papers that are published
by people who train big models.
Although, I think the number of such papers
have decreased in recent years, and most of them
have come out of the open-source community in China.
And so today, I want to talk about a number of these
that I've curated and selected to give you a sense of,
what does scaling at the frontier, at least
open frontier, look like?
What are the things that these people
care about or worry about?
And what would you need to do to speedrun
your way from Chinchilla all the way to, let's say,
Kimi K2, the most recent release that has some scaling details.
So that's going to be the first part of this lecture.
We're going to go through a couple of papers,
and we're going to go through the details.
The second part is going to be a discussion of optimizers
and initializations.
And remember, I spent a nontrivial amount of time
two lectures ago on the selection of batch sizes.
That's going to be an important factor.
And it's also going to be important
thinking about how we're going to tune things
like learning rates.
Those are very sensitive, very important to get right.
And so it turns out that a lot of effort
has been invested into getting those things right.
And we will talk about some of the techniques to do so.
And this may, in fact, even be useful in your day
to day lives of training various language models
because they'll give you a sense of how
to change your hyperparameters and your experiments
as you scale up or down.
So I'm going to spend a nontrivial amount of time
talking about two papers in particular.
They're not the newest papers.
They're not necessarily the most-- actually,
the DeepSeek one might be one of the more detailed ones--
most detailed scaling paper in general.
But I think this hits a sweet spot.
So both of these papers are serious scaling investigations
from people who build reasonably high-performance models.
And importantly, they take pretty different approaches
to some of the key questions that we will ask today.
And so I think they're a good way
to motivate a lot of the rest of the lecture.
So I'm going to talk about these two.
First one is MiniCPM.
This was, I think, back in 2024, high-performance small language
model.
And DeepSeek-- you all are now familiar with this.
I no longer have to justify why I'm talking
about DeepSeek, which is great.
We'll start by talking about MiniCPM, though.
I do like this paper, especially when it first came out.
It felt very fresh and new and at the cutting edge.
Even in 2026, I feel a lot of the things
that the CPM folks did has been informative to us.
I'll talk about this later as I get to the newer papers.
But I think it's becoming the case
that a lot of this classic scaling
stuff, how you set learning rates, how do you do Chinchilla?
those kinds of things I think are now taken for granted.
Everyone just assumes that you know how to do those things.
And so people don't really talk about those as much
anymore in the paper, so it's really nice to talk about some
of these older papers for that reason.
So MiniCPM is an effort by a bunch
of industry academic partnerships folks over
in the Chinese open-source community
to come up with a high-performance, small-ish language model.
And at the time when this came out,
it was basically state of the art for the 1 to 2
billion parameter bracket.
Nowadays, Gemma and other models--
Gemma-- and other models at 2D or 3D are going to be higher
performance.
But these are competitive, well-trained models,
at least as at 2024 standards.
So how do you train these models?
As I said before, we have to get some of these scaling parameters
right.
And one of the things that I'll talk about today that I'll
emphasize quite a bit is, initializations are very important.
Initializations are important because they
allow you to make certain hyperparameters less scale
dependent.
So the first technique that I want
to talk about from this MiniCPM paper
is a special class of initializations called muP.
So muP, the whole point of this approach is to say,
I want to make sure that my optimal learning
rate is the same as I scale up and down.
I talked about this very briefly in the two lectures ago,
so you should hopefully remember that a little bit.
But this is the first real instantiation
that we're going to talk about.
What does that look like specifically?
The MiniCPM paper has a nice list of things to do,
so they scale the embedding output.
They scale the residual connections
by the square root of the number of layers.
They scale the initialization of all
of their matrix-shaped tensors by the fan-in, fan-out ratio.
They scale the learning rates of tensors.
And you should pay attention to this one
because this is exotic if you aren't
used to per parameter learning rates.
And then they also scale the LM heads.
We'll talk about why you do these things,
or how you derive this particular set of scalings.
Suffice to say that you're just going to change up
how you're going to do your initializations
and your learning rates a little bit
in the hopes of stabilizing your learning rates a little bit.
And of course, we're training a small model here,
but we're still wanting to do a nice scaling strategy.
Part of the point of this study is not
that you want to brute force a 1.5 model,
like training hundreds of them.
You want to get the hyperparameters exactly right
the first time.
So you're going to train a bunch much smaller models and then get
a scaling ladder up all the way to your target size of 5x or so.
And so there's about a 5x gap between the biggest model they
train on their ladder and the actual model that they're going
to finally release.
And their goal is going to nail down,
I think, what most people consider
to be the sensitive parameters, like optimal batch size,
learning rate.
And then the token-to-size ratio that we talked about
at Chinchilla.
They also want to replicate a Chinchilla analysis,
much less important to us now and probably to you
even if you're training.
But I'm going to talk about it regardless because there's
one important thing in the way they
do that and that I think has been informative and useful.
So as I said earlier, the whole point
of going through this weird initialization
or nonstandard initialization called
muP is to try to make the optimal learning rate stable.
Is it?
At least in the MiniCPM case, the answer is yes.
In fact, it's very, very clean in their experiments.
They sweep learning rate across a variety of models,
so each line is a model size.
The minimal loss is basically right on 10 to the negative 2.
I guess the minima slightly shifted for the smallest model.
But even then, it's quite close to the minimum.
So this is a nice success case of the muP approach.
We will talk about several other models
and other papers that use muP.
This is not the only way to do it,
but this is one effective way to do it.
And if you can get something like this
now you've removed the need to tune the learning rate.
But of course, even if you have a nice parameterization that
fixes your learning rate to a single of optimum,
your optimal batch size is still not going to be the same.
So the batch size actually varies
as a function of both data set size and model size.
So in their case, they run these model training runs.
So each column of points that you see on these plots
is a training run.
So they have a fixed batch size, and they
increase the number of tokens processed, I guess,
from bottom to top.
And then they ask, OK, we've done
many of these training runs.
What is the optimal batch size fitting these quadratic curves
onto each of these lines over here, this equal loss contour?
What they find is this kind of optimal batch size
scaling as a function of the number of tokens processed,
and they do this across different model sizes.
Maybe you would not be surprised by this, given the nice scalings
that we saw in the Kaplan paper for critical batch sizes.
But the optimal batch size does have a power law structure
with respect to the target loss.
And so we see exactly the Kaplan-style analysis
of, if your loss is lower on the left,
your batch size should be bigger,
critical batch size scaling.
And so now given a particular loss
target, which you can back out from the scaling laws,
you can basically set what the optimal or critical batch sizes
that would give you the best trade-offs.
So there's a nice clean trend here.
This will let you set batch size very easily and precisely.
So those two, the batch size and the learning rate scaling,
they're going to come back over and over again.
Those are arguably the most important and sensitive
parameters to do scaling laws on.
But I'll talk about one last thing in the MiniCPM paper
that I think is important.
So remember, to do Chinchilla, we
need to train a lot of different models.
So we're going to, let's say, do IsoFLOPs.
That means I'm going to fix a FLOPs budget,
and I'm going to vary my trade-offs between number
of tokens and model size.
And to do that, I'm going to, let's
say, increase the amount of data I train on,
so increase the number of sequences.
但当我增加序列数量，
记住每一个都会得到不同的学习率
调度。
你们都在用余弦学习率训练。
余弦学习率看起来不太一样。
你需要知道最终的总
预算，才能用余弦调度来训练。
所以这就引出一个烦人的事实，
那就是你得一直重新训练你的模型。
如果你想训练一个 800 万序列的模型，
你不能从 400 万序列模型的末尾重新开始。
你必须从头开始，
因为你的学习率调度
从根本上就不同。
这真的很烦人。
从某种意义上说，这就像二次方的成本，
因为你得一直重新开始你的运行，
从起点开始。
这看起来很浪费，我想很多其他人
也这么觉得。
我认为 MiniCPM 论文中一个不错的解决方案
就是现在所谓的 warmup stable decay
学习率。
或者这是这个的流行叫法，
它基本上就是一个大梯形。
所以你有一个预热阶段。
预热阶段通常被定义为
一个恒定的步数，而不是
你训练目标的一个比例。
所以这与你的训练时长无关。
你有一段相当长的运行，在这期间你保持
学习率恒定。
这就是稳定阶段。
然后在最后，你会相当快速地衰减
到 0。
这就是衰减阶段。
一般来说，衰减阶段大约是你
整个训练运行的 10% 到 20%。
所以你会在绝大部分训练
运行期间保持稳定，然后做一个非常快速的衰减，
to usually about 10% of your maximum
learning rate at the very end here.
And that's a very typical warmup, stable,
decay learning rate.
And why do we do this?
What's the point of doing this?
Well, we do WSD because now we can
restart a run at any point at the end of the stable phase.
So if I want to reuse a run and train it for longer,
I'll just roll back my training to the last stable checkpoint.
And then I'll just run the stable learning rates forward
and then decay the model down to 0.
So this provides a very easy way for us
to essentially run scale in data experiments
without constantly rerunning your experiments.
So you do have to redecay every time,
but that's maybe 10% of the total cost.
It's a much better situation to be repeatedly decaying
than to repeatedly rerun your pre-training runs.
And this is a very common trick that's used in many places.
I'll show, I guess, a performance comparison.
There have been many plots of this form.
I think, who was the most recent folks that were--
maybe it was Martin Jaggi and others,
I think, over at ETH had an extensive study
of WSD performance.
But I think a lot of papers have shown similar things of,
you have a well-tuned cosine learning curve.
This is the orange line over here.
And then you've got various WSD curves.
And WSD curves always look a little bit funky
because it looks like you're way underperforming until you
hit the decay phase, where suddenly you
reclaim all of your gains.
And then you match or even sometimes exceed
the cosine learning rate performance.
Anecdotally, I think if you talk to a bunch of people training
networks, I think a lot of people
will say the cosine is slightly better in many cases.
But WSD is basically as good in many other situations.
It is a very versatile default learning rate.
It doesn't necessarily suffer from having
to rerun if you want to just continue runs.
It is very cool though, to see just how much of an impact
learning rate decay has if you haven't played with that before.
This part of decaying the learning rate
is just incredibly important to getting the final annealing
parts of your training together.
OK, so that's the comparison there.
So now that we're equipped with WSD SGD style learning rates,
Chinchilla style analyses are actually very easy.
What you're going to do is you're
going to essentially run one long run,
and then you'll just rewind the checkpoints and then repeatedly
decay.
And that will give you sweeps along the data dimension.
And then you'll also do sweeps along the model dimension.
You can do flops or any other kind of analysis
that you would like.
The MiniCPM authors, for whatever reason,
choose to try to replicate methods
1 and 3, which, to me, are the least reliable
of the Chinchilla methods.
But they do get fairly nice looking scaling curves.
If you look at the MiniCPM Chinchilla method 1,
they see nice, lower envelopes that look mostly linear
across these, which is good.
And then method 3, they get nice, smooth scaling
for the most part in both the compute
to non-embedding parameter trade-off.
So it seems like, for the most part,
they get reasonable Chinchilla-looking fits.
One thing I will point out is that they
get pretty different exponents for their overall joint fit
compared to Chinchilla.
They claim in the paper that this
means that they should be training with way more
pieces of text than Chinchilla.
It is highly unclear to me whether this is really true
or whether their Chinchilla fits are a little bit
strange relative to the Chinchilla paper.
OK, I'll stop here for a moment in case someone
has questions about MiniCPM.
Maybe the main couple things to take away
is, one is the use of muP is a useful trick,
I guess, to try to stabilize how your learning rate changes
over scales.
And then the second thing maybe to remember
is the WSD learning rate.
That's just a very common trick.
You should all know about this learning rate.
That's a basic thing to know.
OK, good.
All right, so then I'll move on to DeepSeek.
This is the original DeepSeek paper,
before they started talking about MOEs and all
these other very cool things.
And I think, even at the very first DeepSeek paper,
you could tell that these were very serious people
because I think DeepSeek LLM, even now, is,
I think, one of the more nicely executed scaling analyses
in the open world.
And I feel like they have lots of great taste
in the experiments that they run.
So even before R1 and so on came out,
it was kind of clear that these people were going places.
All right, so DeepSeek takes a very different scaling strategy
than MiniCPM and several others in trying to optimize
their hyperparameters.
They're not going to really do muP.
They're not going to do this interesting scaling adjustments.
Instead, they're going to try to fit a scaling law
to estimate both the optimal batch size
and the optimal learning rate.
So we that the learning rate and batch sizes
should actually change with scale.
But if the way in which they change
are predictable, just like a scaling law,
then we're good to go.
We don't really need to worry about very much.
So what they do is they basically run extensive grid
searches at various different scales,
and they try to find the optimum.
So this is an example of the kind of thing they're doing.
They're sweeping learning rates.
They're sweeping batch sizes.
And they're looking at the terminal loss
if they're processing a particular number of tokens.
So they fixed the compute, and then they vary these two.
They'll do this across several different scales,
and then they'll basically try to identify
what the lowest loss is, so in this case, the lightest color.
So they'll put a little star there,
and then they'll do this across scales.
So if you do this across sufficiently many scales,
you will get a plot that looks a little like this.
And this plot is saying, OK, I'm going
to vary my nonembedding training FLOPs across some range.
And you can see these gray dots over here.
And as I vary this, my optimal batch size will change.
Remember, the optimal batch size is
derived by looking at these big grids and finding the minimizer.
And I will get something that looks like a line.
The optimal batch size should scale
with my nonembedding FLOPs.
And similarly for my optimal learning rate,
I'll get a bunch of gray dots in my nonembedding FLOPs range.
And then I can fit a line to that
to try to estimate what my optimal learning
rate should look like.
So this is fairly nice.
And I guess one thing I'll point out
is, their full runs are on the star.
These are the runs that they chose.
At higher FLOPs, they have much higher batch sizes
and much lower learning rates.
The stars are the things they actually ran for their big runs.
These fits look reasonable for the batches.
This does look like a line.
The one on the learning rate--
I'm not quite sure that constitutes
the best linear fits that I've seen in my life,
but I guess it works.
It's probably fine.
The models do train.
The models do get reasonable things.
I think this is the one, I would say,
like drawback of the learning rates approach.
It's not really clear that if you try to do this grid search
kind of thing, unless your grid is in the right place,
you've got a lot of quantization error.
And then you're not getting very good scaling law fits,
and you end up with something that looks like an arbitrary
linear thing going on.
OK, oh, yeah, sorry.
How come for the same number of training steps there,
you get multiple data points with a large range
of optimal values?
Why is it that you get a large range of optimal learning rates
for different training FLOPs?
Is that the question on the y-axis over here?
Yeah, so the reason I think there
is because of the changes to the model sizes
and things like this.
So 2024 was back in the era where
I think every open model builder was replicating
the entire scaling law stack.
And so DeepSeek also complements the learning rate analysis
with basically a Chinchilla replication.
And to do that, they're also going to do
the same thing as MiniCPM.
They're going to follow the WSD-style learning rate.
They have a weird little variation
where they do two decay phases instead of one.
I am not really sure why this is.
It hasn't really been a thing that has taken off afterwards,
but it is a thing that they do.
Regardless, the whole point here is to say,
WSD is an effective approach.
And you can use that to replicate Chinchilla.
And DeepSeek has much nicer scaling curves
than MiniCPM because of their choice to go IsoFLOPs.
So they get these very nice, clean sweeps
across the fixed FLOPs ranges.
And then they also get fairly nice and clean
Chinchilla-style trade-offs as before.
So this allows them to essentially replicate
the Chinchilla results and get a similar kind of data model
scaling law.
Really, the point that I'm showing with this is just to say, look, the Chinchilla laws have
been replicated by other people at large-ish compute ranges.
So that analysis is generally sound.
Finally, I think, this is the--
I'm a little bit sad that these kinds of plots
are now somewhat rare in open-source release papers,
but this is really the final punchline
of a lot of scaling law work.
You train a bunch of small, curated models
at smaller compute ranges, and then you draw out the power law.
And then in the end, you get something
pretty close to reality if you scale out enough.
So the two stars are the models that they actually trained.
The gray dots are their scaling law fits.
And they're getting pretty good predictions on their star.
I mean, it could be better, but it's not bad at all.
And so they're able to get some pretty accurate scaling law
predictions on real open-source models that they've trained.
OK, I'll actually stop here.
If people have questions about the DeepSeek stuff,
feel free to ask them.
I think my one-line summary here is to say,
this is the other approach to dealing
with the sensitive hyperparameters.
You can either attempt to stabilize them,
or you can attempt to just scaling law
fit them and then just go with the scaling law.
And DeepSeek represents the more fit the scaling law approach
to this problem.
Good, OK.
So there are other models, more recent ones
that have nice scaling laws that they talk about.
As I said before, though, I think a lot of this work is now--
what's the-- it's all known to everybody.
And so no one is really putting a lot of this stuff
into big sections into the paper.
So if you look at Qwen 2.5, they say something like,
OK, well, we need to tune some optimal hyperparameters,
like batch sizes and learning rates.
So we do a bunch of scaling experiments
to figure out what the optimum are.
And then we have a scaling law, and we predict the optimum.
And then we're able to do that even for MoEs.
So this is basically the same thing as the DeepSeek analysis
that they're talking about in Qwen 2.5.
Same thing with Qwen 3.
By the time it's Qwen 3, they say,
all right, we've already figured out what to do in Qwen 2.5.
We're just doing exactly the same thing.
So this has become part of a very standard recipe
that you use in order to nail down the optimal learning
rates and batches.
Kimi K2 is probably the newest paper
that I'll talk about of the series.
At this point, I'm just going to quickly go
through several papers maybe to give you
an overview of what people are doing
in terms of scaling work in the open-source model releases.
So Kimi K2 and a few others have focused on essentially MoE
scaling laws.
So it's 2026.
Most people know how to do a Chinchilla scaling law or even
a learning rate scaling law.
What things are new?
Well, a lot of these companies are now switching to MoEs,
fully switching to MoEs.
And if you're doing that, you really want to know,
am I training the right amount of active parameters?
And so they're doing things, like, OK, we're
going to vary the flops and look at my losses.
And I'm going to do so for different levels of sparsity
so that I can figure out how much sparsity helps or hurts
my losses.
And their conclusion, of course, is
if you look at the different sparsity levels, the more sparse
your network, the better your validation loss,
given a FLOP—unsurprising.
But now the fact that they can quantitatively
know what the relationship is between sparsity and loss
means that they can make more rational decisions
about how much sparsity to put into their model.
And they look at this, and they say, OK,
what we're going to do is we're going to use sparsity of 48,
because at that point we're hitting diminishing returns
on our scaling loss.
So you can see how this kind of analysis used to justify different architectural decisions
across different open-source releases.
Hunyuan, which is another open-source MoE from a few years
ago now, they do a very similar thing.
I think every company, once they switch to the MoE,
has to do this kind of MoE scaling law
to figure out how the number of activated
parameters or the amount of sparsity
changes training loss.
And then they redo a lot of these analyses.
So for example, in Hunyuan's case,
they end up with a 96 data point per active parameter ratio.
In their case, they're fixing the sparsity level.
And so that's not a thing that they're searching over.
LLaMA 3 also has some nice scaling laws.
Unfortunately, they're not particularly useful ones.
They do IsoFLOP-style scaling and get
slightly different but similar ratios for token-to-model.
The most interesting thing that they do in terms of scaling
in LLaMA 3 is the plot on the right
here, which is, they have the usual scaling
law, which is the left panel.
That's saying, if I have more compute,
then the logprob on the answer for a benchmark
decays consistently.
And on the right side, they show, OK, well,
if you have better log loss, then
the downstream accuracy also goes up.
So they're basically saying, well,
we can just fit a sigmoid on these purple points.
And that might give us a sense of how good
these different models are.
You can see their systematic deviations from the curve.
So I don't really know if I would really
buy that this curve is like the one truth that's going on.
But you can certainly see that it
is consistent with a sigmoidal scaling
mapping from the loss to the accuracy, which I think
is very useful because we've been talking only
about log losses.
But there is a tight coupling in some cases, or in many cases,
between log losses and downstream accuracy.
And then for one last paper that I
want to talk about for scaling, MiniMax-01 from last year
had this nice set of scaling experiments
where they were doing the exact kind of thing
I was saying is a useful affordance of scaling
from two lectures ago, and that is architecture variations.
And so they wanted to understand,
OK, I have lightning attention, which
is some kind of a linear attention architecture.
I have a softmax version like full attention,
and I have a hybrid version that mixes the two.
How do these things scale?
Is it the case that if I scale up, one of them
will get much worse than the other?
And so you can see, they're replicating essentially
the Kaplan plots of, as I increase FLOPs,
how do the learning curves change?
And is the number of parameters that I
need different for different levels of compute
for these different architectures?
And the answer is, for the most part, no,
that hybrid and lightning and softmax
are all comparable for the most part.
And they require similar model sizes.
And this set of plots is used to justify
their use of the hybrid architecture
in the actual deployed system.
So this is exactly the kind of decision making that you would
do based upon a scaling law.
So that's basically what I wanted
to cover for the recent scaling law recipes
from the various companies.
So the two things, as I said before, for the DeepSeek recipe.
Really, the key thing is the scaling analysis
on the batch and learning rate.
This is the scaling-based approach.
And MiniCPM follows more of a muP-style approach
to try to get invariances.
And then we see some trends.
We see that Kimi and Qwen and others, or in Hunyuan,
are doing these MoE scaling experiments
as they switch to MoEs.
We see some architecture work by MiniMax,
and we also see some IsoFLOPs analysis being
replicated by several others.
And to return to our previous point,
the point here is, I think a lot of companies
are now less detailed because the core scaling
machinery, like doing Chinchilla or doing learning rate scaling,
is now fairly well understood by everybody.
So there's no necessarily extra value
in showing those experiments for some of these releases.
Or at least that's my guess for why
we have much fewer of these kinds of experiments
in the release.
OK, I'll take one minute and then pause
and let you digest and ask a question or two, in case you
have questions for this part.
OK, so all these cover the proofing stage.
So my question is, what changes and what
do not change when post training is a standardized process
for model development?
Yeah, so the question was about, what
changes about this when you do-- or when
you think about post training, I guess, broadly?
I think that's still a big, open question.
There's no great way to do fully integrated scaling
with post-training accounted for,
because post-training can sometimes really change
the nature of what pre-training you should do.
The closest things that I can think
of to thinking about post-training
is there's been some work on understanding coverage
or diversity notions in pre-training that would help
predict what happens in post-training,
but it's still pretty nascent work.
I don't think there's any good answer to the question of,
what do we do about synergy with post-training?
Cool.
OK, so now we're going to talk about the other piece.
So I think the two remaining parts of this lecture
map on cleanly to the two examples.
So I'm going to talk about one approach, one set of approaches,
which is about scaling laws for learning rates,
batch sizes, and optimizers.
That corresponds to the DeepSeek approach to the world.
And then I'm going to talk about the muP stuff.
That's the MiniCPM approach to the world.
Can we just reparameterize everything
to make it so that we don't have to worry about scale?
So we're going to now talk about the DeepSeek approach.
How do we scale learning rate properly?
And so there's going to be a hyperparameter part
and an optimizer choice part.
And I'm going to draw quite a bit
from this pretty recent preprint from the StepFun folks.
I don't think there's a great, really, truly
reliable, robust study on hyperparameters,
especially learning rates.
But this is probably getting somewhat close.
The StepFun folks train credible large models and release them.
And they burned a ton of compute in grid
searching the space of hyperparameters in this scaling
law study.
So I'll go through this and show you
some intriguing empirical phenomena
about how learning rates, batch size, and all of those
affect downstream losses.
So lots of people have talked about lots of different ways
of scaling, learning rate and batch sizes as roughly
as a function of compute.
And the StepFun survey-- not survey paper,
the hyperparameter tuning paper has this very nice table
that captures a lot of this.
And I'll point out a couple of different things.
Some of this we already know.
So the very top row, this OpenAI scaling law-- this from Kaplan.
If you look at the batch size over there,
notice how it says 2e18, capital L to the exponent.
That's critical batch sizes, right.
It's basically saying, you should scale your batch size
as a function of your terminal loss.
Great.
DeepSeek we just saw.
This is the compute-based scaling loss for both learning
rate and batch size.
And there's been a couple of other folks
that have proposed various kinds of scaling, including MiniCPM,
which we talked about as well.
Another important thing that I want to point out
is that these formulas for learning rate and batch sizes,
they don't even have the same inputs.
People don't even seem to agree, what
are the variables that should affect these learning rates?
Like, the OpenAI one is terminal loss.
Whereas, the StepFun folks, they claim
that the right batch size scaling is a function of the data.
So there's a lot of different disagreements about the nature
of scaling for hyperparameters.
And I think one thing I'll say as I go through this: not to take even this last row as gospel.
A lot of these things are pretty brittle in many ways,
but the experiments and the phenomena
are things that you can learn well from.
So I'll do that.
So the design of this paper is very similar to the DeepSeek
one.
They're just going to train a ton of models
to grid out both the learning rate space and the batch size
space and do them across a range of models and range
of data set sizes.
And by doing so, they hope to essentially saturate
the hyperparameter space for a set of small models
and then nail down what the optimum is.
And much like in the DeepSeek design,
they're going to be-- after they grid up
the space-- in this case, they have a contour plot.
But the underlying objects are just,
they run a bunch of models.
They aim to try to minimize the losses.
And the contour plots are quite nice.
I feel like they give a good visualization.
They ran a pretty high resolution grid.
And thanks to that, one of the things that we can see
is that they can actually plot out
a fairly high-resolution contour of what the hyperparameter
space looks like.
In this case, this is a slice at 1b parameters and 100b tokens,
I believe.
And you can see on the right side,
that surface is the hyperparameter landscape.
As a function of the batch size, which is one axis, and learning
rate, which is the other axis, how does the loss
change if you fix the total amount of data in the model?
Now, we see that each slice, if you
fix a batch size or you fix a learning rate--
each slice is kind of nice and convex.
And it's almost even smooth.
And this is quite nice because it
means that you can search for the optimal hyperparameter
fairly nicely, and you can be confident that the minima is not
too far off.
This was very jaggedy.
You might have some very serious doubts
about whether this kind of program of gridding the space
is even viable.
Also, this should maybe give you some nice intuition
about the smoothness of the hyperparameter space in general.
And I think there's actually one really interesting
general scaling trend.
And looking at other related papers to this topic, I think,
I don't know if I've seen any contradicting evidence
to this observation.
So I think the one thing that seems very interesting
and one of the key takeaways of this work
is, essentially, if you're looking at the optimal batch
size, the only thing that seems to depend on
is the total amount of data that you're training on.
So this right-hand plot is the one to look at.
So x-axis here is the amount of data that you're training on.
The different colored dots-- those are different models.
Notice how the different colored dots seem
to follow roughly the same trend line here,
fairly predictable one.
And this is in log-log scale, so you
should expect some of a power law that's a function of D.
On the left panel, we have the dependence of learning rate.
And we see that this is a very different behavior.
So if you go from blue all the way to this pink color right,
bigger models have smaller optimal learning rate.
And larger amounts of data have higher optimal learning rate,
which is counterintuitive, actually.
And so this might be a little fragile.
There are other kinds of papers that
argue that the dependence on D should be reversed.
But the trends here are at least on this experiment,
are quite clear.
And one final thing that I want to point out
is, the learning rates are actually pretty robust.
And I think this is backed up by a lot of experiences
and experiments that people have.
I think people have a sense of-- actually as a poll,
do people know what a good hyperparameter is?
If you were told to train a language model tomorrow,
would it be 1e negative 3, 1e negative 4?
I feel like we roughly have a sense of, actually,
this range of hyperparameters for learning rates is generally
a good starting point.
And that is generally true.
So the scaling laws that they got actually
transfer over to, for example, MoEs to a certain extent.
The yellow stars, which might be a little harder to see,
are the predictions from their scaling laws.
The red x's are the optima that are derived directly
on the MoEs.
And so you switch to an MoE.
You don't end up with a very different scaling
law, as long as you're roughly controlling
for active parameters.
The one thing that does seem a little bit more
potentially dicey is, as you shift
the training data, the optimal learning
rates and the optimal batch sizes do shift a little bit,
which means that all of these phenomena are likely contingent.
The specific numbers that are in these scaling laws and so on
are potentially contingent to the data
that you train on more so than others.
And so I want to flash this back up before I move on.
So you end up with some of simple scaling
law at the end, which says, OK, batch size maybe
should be roughly square root of the number of data
times some constant.
Your learning rate should scale upwards
with batch size or upwards with data
but downwards with the model size.
And that's a surprising effect but not maybe crazy,
because these experiments often, in many cases,
are assuming Chinchilla-like scaling, in which
case, those two would cancel.
And as you increase compute, your learning rate
should go down.
And hopefully, that Chinchilla comment was clear.
What I mean is when you're scaling by Chinchilla,
N and D are both driven by compute.
And as compute goes up, you expect your learning rate
to go down.
And so you will end up with something like the DeepSeek
Law, where the learning rate decreases with compute,
and the batch size increases with compute,
albeit with different exponents than the DeepSeek Law.
Cool.
OK, so in some sense, this is the newest and most
large-scale version of the DeepSeek analysis.
And this is one way that, if you were
doing the scaling-law-style approach,
you would approach this problem of fitting a learning rate.
So that's the hyperparameter story.
If someone has questions, feel free to stop me.
And then next, right after, I'm going to move on
to talking about optimizers.
I think this is one thing I didn't have time to talk about
in the architectures lecture.
That was already a pretty packed lecture.
But I think it would be a disservice if I
don't talk about optimizers.
And optimizers are scale dependent,
so this is a good place to put them and talk about some
of the latest and greatest developments in optimizers
and their relationship with scale.
Oh, yeah?
So I guess I'm trying to figure out how to interpret this.
Does that mean we should just take the scaling laws that we
have and then apply them, rather than running our own grid
search?
Yeah, I mean, I think it depends what regime you're in.
The question is like-- oh, sorry, I
have to repeat it for the online folks-- is should we just take
the scaling law and run them, or should we just
do our own grid search?
It does depend on the amount of compute budget that you have
and how much you need to nail it.
I do think, for example, maybe the StepFun law--
if you're in the right compute regime,
like close to where they were running the grid,
these are probably really good defaults.
I would bet on these over something I pull out of my hat.
That said, if you were doing your own big pre-training run,
you're probably going to have minor differences.
Someone might say, I really believe
we should have a big weight decay.
My architecture has a big weight decay.
We don't know necessarily that those things
are going to scale the same.
And so you might want to actually redo a lot of this.
And this is why I think a lot of the reports I showed
you were redoing Chinchilla, redoing all
these things, because there's enough minor differences
that people want to check and make sure
that they're roughly first-order correct with these results.
I think this will come up again in this next optimizer part.
And I was talking about this with [MUTED] earlier,
which is, scaling laws have this very scientific feel to them.
It's like, yes, fit these lines and extrapolate them.
But ultimately, a big part of scaling laws is still vibes.
It's like, do I really believe that the experiment setting
of this StepFun survey is similar enough to mine
that they will transfer?
We can't possibly, right.
There are always tiny differences.
Good, OK, so now I get to talk about optimizers.
And I think there's been some really exciting developments
in LLM optimizers, and maybe even
deep learning optimizers in general
over the past year or two.
And so this is an exciting time to talk about them.
And so a story that I want to start with
and one that should maybe motivate this subsection
is this comparison over here, or maybe we'll
start on this left panel.
So this is from NanoGPT speedrun, which
inspired our assignment 1.
And there you have a really teeny, tiny model
that you're training on a fairly short amount of time,
and you want to get the, I forget, 3 point-some loss
as quickly as possible.
And many people have been hill climbing on this benchmark.
And I think one of the more remarkable things that
have happened on the benchmark is as a benchmark called
muon in purple over here came and got really significant gains
over Adam, which is blue.
It's right underneath the green line over there.
So you can just look at the green
and the purple and that gap.
And you say, wow, lots of big gains
from just changing the optimizer to this muon thing.
And it's not even slower than Adam, much slower than Adam.
That's great.
But then there's a question of, well,
is this thing actually good at scale?
And then you go and run some scaling studies,
and maybe they're not quite as good.
This is a really tricky and important part
of how we do research.
We have a small-scale experiment.
We have something that's scale-dependent, for sure,
like an optimizer.
And then we see really big gains in the small scale.
What do we do about the large scale?
And more than providing a solid, concrete prescription,
I want us to maybe almost even provide a story here so
that you can get a sense of what we can do
and what things we can't necessarily know.
So actually, before I move on to the next slide,
and this kind of thing happens all the time, where you're like,
come up with a great thing small scale.
And it just doesn't maybe pan out large scale.
So what's the difference?
I'm going to spend a few slides talking about Kaiyue and Tengyu
and Percy and David's paper on basically doing
a large-scale set of experiments on comparing optimizers
and trying to do that comparison better.
And there's a lot to learn about scaling and other things
from that, but also just standard deep learning stuff.
There's really basic things.
Like, the hyperparameters for different models are different.
So if you're scaling things up, maybe they even
have different scaling exponents.
So you have to tune Adam really well.
So if you tune it badly you get this darker, brown line.
And you're like, wow, this thing is much worse
than all these other algorithms that I have over here
on the left.
But then you change the learning rate a little bit.
And you're like, wow, actually, all my gains went away.
Similarly on the right, you can have cases where maybe you've
tuned your learning rate well.
But now you've got other stuff like weight decay
that is not optimally tuned.
And so if you use the same weight decay,
then you're certainly going to get a much worse result
for this green line.
If you pick this small weight decay,
you'll get a much worse result for this green line
than if you pick the optimal weight decay.
So there's all sorts of pretty tricky things going on,
technically not a scaling thing, but a very important
general empirical machine learning thing
that I want to point out.
But maybe more relevant to the discussion in this class right
now is the scale dependence of these things.
And I think this is a good case study and example of how
to really think about algorithm development
as a function of scale, because to me, there
are two variables that are always important when
thinking about scale.
And this paper exposes, to most extent, both of them.
So one axis is compute.
And if you're fixing the model size to data ratio,
like the two are coupled together,
then this is essentially a compute axis on the x-axis here.
So whenever you're doing a study essentially scale up the compute
and look at the trends as a function of scale.
And we see right here that if we look
at the relative speedup between Adam, which
is at 1.0 by definition, and all these other alternatives,
we see that muons are really good at small scale.
And that gain diminishes down as we increase in scale.
That's not really necessarily the picture
that you want to see.
There's another axis that you should always
be vigilant of if you're doing algorithm development,
and the other one that you should be vigilant of
is the Chinchilla ratio.
So the Chinchilla ratio can be thought of.
It is the ratio between how much data
you have and the amount of model you have.
And this is a really, really, really important parameter
because some algorithms work well
in the overparameterized case where
you have a way bigger model than you have lots of data.
Maybe your algorithm adds some implicit regularization.
Or maybe it is data inefficient, but it works well
because of compute reasons.
So some algorithms might work well at the small Chinchilla
ratio case.
In contrast, other algorithms might work well
in the large Chinchilla ratio case, where
you have lots of data per unit parameter
because you can pack knowledge more efficiently
into the parameters.
So this is a big, big big confounder.
Even papers that I think have pretty good hygiene in doing
scaling experiments on the model size axis often neglect
to or just don't have the compute
to study the Chinchilla token to parameter ratio.
And this turns out to be surprisingly important
a lot of time.
In this case, it's not.
In this case, you see that the optimizer gains
are pretty consistent.
The ratio is between all the lines
are the same at different Chinchilla ratios.
But this is not always the case.
You always want to be vigilant about both of these scaling
factors.
That's quite important.
And then I'm going to also point out,
if you have a new algorithm or a new setting,
establishing scaling is quite nontrivial.
So I've taken this from one of--
Will Held was working with Marin,
which was Percy's open-source language model training project.
And there they were basically trying
to prove out a particular set of hyperparameters.
This is even like a new algorithm.
So this is cautious AdamC, which is
like an Adam variant, square root, batch size
scaling and a bunch of other standard-looking things.
And they're doing essentially the same Chinchilla analysis
that you've seen all the other papers do.
But because this is not necessarily a paper,
this is a bunch of people doing experiments,
you don't just publish the successful one.
They have the niceness of publishing their failed runs.
And the example here is that they're
doing basically standard Chinchilla stuff,
and it's looking great.
If you go up to this dashed vertical line at 10
to the 20 something, this is a really beautiful-looking scaling
loft here.
And then, as you scale up, it's like, well, it's
a little bit worse.
It's a lot worse.
And then, wow, now that run is not so good anymore.
So it's totally blown up on you.
And the point here is that even good-looking scaling
trends for many orders of magnitude can suddenly bite you.
It can deviate from linear, and then it
can then blow up immediately.
And in their case, the fix here is just
picking more careful muP-style parameterizations.
Optimizer changes.
They switch to a different kind of optimizer,
and they get nicer scaling across more orders of magnitude.
But the point here is to say, when I go back here,
and I say, OK, well, you should all do scaling experiments,
you should scale all your learning rates
and so on, that's not easy.
You end up fairly nontrivial fraction of the time
with plots that look like this.
And it's all horrible, and you're not
quite sure what has gone wrong.
Good.
OK.
And then, so the last thing I want to end with
is just talking a little bit about muon
and the closing of the muon story.
So I feel like I have to talk about muon in a little bit
more detail than I already have, just because it's
beginning to be integrated into a large scale model
training runs.
That's the inclusion criteria for a lot of new research
topics for the class.
Has it been in a big training run?
And muon now checks that mark.
And it's also just an interesting algorithm,
so I'll mention it and talk about it for a few minutes
and then move on.
So in gradient descent, we usually
have a fairly simple thing that's happening.
Ignore line for the moment, sorry, line 5 for the moment.
And then you're going to get roughly
a standard momentum-based optimizer.
I take a gradient.
I add it to B of t.
This is my momentum step, so I continue my momentum
from before with parameter mu.
And then I update my parameters based on this momentum gradient.
Very standard momentum gradient stuff.
But then I think the really interesting and, to me at least,
a bit of an out of the box set of ideas is to say,
well, gradients have this property that they treat,
all the parameters are the same.
But we know that not all the parameters in a language model,
or even a deep neural network, are the same.
Some parameters are like vector parameters.
They belong to the RMS norm.
Some parameters are matrix parameters,
like for the attention or for MLPs.
And matrix parameters are probably
different than vector parameters.
And so that's the starting point for this idea
and I think a really interesting one.
And so the one thing that you could do about matrix parameters
is you can start to look at their spectra.
They are matrices.
Matrices have eigenvalues and singular values.
And so you can do things to the singular values.
And so what you do here in Muon is this fairly simple idea.
You compute a gradient.
You take a momentum step.
And now I take my update B of t.
And instead of directly applying it
to my parameters in line 6, what I'm going to do
is I'm going to do this NewtonSchultz thing,
NewtonSchultz 5 to be specific.
And what that is it's going to orthogonalize the B of t matrix.
And so I've written the operation down there on the bottom.
Let's say I take B of t.
I write it as singular value decomposition, USV transpose.
And then I make all of my singular values 1.
So if my singular values are really big,
I'll shrink them back to unit.
If they're really small, I'll expand them
back up to being unit.
And then I take UV transpose, and that's my new update
that I'm going to apply.
If you want intuition for this, and you already
have intuition for something like adagrad or these other,
or Adam even.
In adagrad or Adam, you're going to divide
by the size of the gradient.
So every coordinate is roughly going to be the same size.
In muon, you are operating in the spectral norm instead.
So every kind of direction is going to be unit size.
And notice that this only makes sense for a matrix.
I can only define this notion of a singular value decomposition
for a matrix valued B of t.
So the interesting thing about muon
is it's a matrix optimizer, so you apply it
to these matrix valued parameters.
And for the vector-valued ones, you
might still use something like AdamW
because those don't really have any interaction
with the NewtonSchultz term.
Also, NewtonSchultz is an approximation
to that operation that only uses matrix multiplies.
So it's systems efficient and not
exactly the orthogonalization.
But OK, why have I spent all this time talking about muon?
Well, first of all, it's very powerful for things
like the NanoGPT speedrun.
It was discovered for this set of things.
And so you might think that it works well.
As I said in the previous slide, there
have been some scaling studies that
have argued that the gain for muon decreases as scale goes up.
But then I want to close off this story, which, I think,
initially this came out.
And I was like, wow, muon is interesting.
I wonder if anyone will scale it up.
And then [INAUDIBLE] and others scaled up muon.
And they said, well, maybe it doesn't work super well.
And I thought the story was closed here.
I was like, well, maybe this is done.
No one will spend the big compute to scale this guy up
to the full pre-training size.
And then Kimi K2 comes out, and that whole model
is trained with muon, fully with muon,
with a few bells and whistles to prevent muon
from blowing up on you.
They found a whole bunch of instability issues.
But Kimi K2 is an outstandingly good model.
It's a very good model, and the training curves look reasonable.
And so really, what this suggests is like,
well, muon worked at scale.
Is it better than Adam?
Kimi K2 certainly doesn't have any ablation,
so we don't know at that scale.
But it is certainly a valid and workable solution.
And so what's the point of this story?
It's to say, it's really hard to tell whether something
works at scale.
It's very, very hard.
But thus far, a lot of small scale experiments
and transferring them up to large scale
has been the way by which we do science.
And so you still want to respect things
like the NanoGPT speedrun.
We learn quite a bit from that and get good ideas.
And then eventually, they make their way to the big models.
We'll see if people continue to do ablations at big scale
and really nail down, is muon better than AdamW at scale
and so on?
Those are interesting questions to which we don't yet
have the answers.
OK, I'll pause here for a moment.
This is the end of my optimizer section.
I want to make sure everyone's good, also especially because I
was talking about muon.
And that's a whole new can of worms
that I haven't talked about much before.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE] letter [INAUDIBLE] faster on GPU?
OK, [INAUDIBLE].
Great.
Yeah, the question was, is SVD fast on GPUs?
SVD is not fast on GPUs, but they're not doing SVD.
What they're doing is NewtonSchultz.
NewtonSchultz is a matrix multiply only finite iteration
algorithm that approximates the process of orthogonalizing
a matrix.
So there's several clever pieces here.
One of them is the idea of treating it
as a matrix on its own.
And then there's this orthogonalization idea,
and then there's the systems piece
of doing it with Newton-Schulz.
So those are all important, interesting pieces?
Yeah, back there?
Are hyperparameters for nontrivial [INAUDIBLE] ones?
Are the hyperparameters here-- no, they're different, yeah.
I think there are several people that
have been working on this Muon-style line of work.
And one of them, I think, like Jeremy Bernstein,
I think he's been saying, actually
every layer should have its own learning rate.
I think the ultimate limit of this, like, you go from-- or even, sorry,
every layer should have its own optimizer.
The ultimate limit of this is to say,
every parameter in a transformer is different.
Why not have a different optimizer for each one of them?
And so you would have to tune hyperparameters
for each one of them as well, which I do not want to do.
But that's maybe the future of optimization.
Yes?
What's the validity of like--
like, on the learning rate and batch size,
you just consider these two things.
And then you pick the best out of those,
and then you can use it to tune other things.
But do these things interact with each other?
Yeah, or maybe the version of the question that I interpreted
was, a lot of these people are just
tuning learning rate and batch size.
And they do this on the grid.
But presumably, these things interact with a whole bunch
of other hyperparameters.
Aren't you worried about that?
And I think, in general, yes, you
are worried about hyperparameter interactions.
But realistically, they grow exponentially.
This is not a thing where you can grid out the whole space.
And so I think the thing that people often do
is they grid the stuff that's most concerning and most
sensitive.
And learning rates are very important.
I think, if you ever tune stuff, learning rates
are the most important thing to tune.
So they very aggressively go on that.
And then stuff like weight decay,
they might do a univariate sweep afterwards
to be locally optimal with respect to those parameters.
Good.
OK.
All right, so the final part of this lecture
is I want to talk about muP.
muP is a bit of a mysterious object.
Even with many papers written about it
and, in fact, even many implementations,
I don't think all of them even agree
on what the underlying math is or what the underlying
implementation should be.
But there's a core set of ideas that are shared,
and it does seem generally effective.
And so I'll talk about my interpretation
of the whole program, let's call it.
So the goal hopefully is very clear.
And I think this picture is the goal, the picture being, well,
if we increase the size of our model,
in this case, just width, our optimal learning rate normally
shifts.
But ideally, we want the optimal learning rate
to be the same, no matter what.
That is the game that we would like to play.
And the knobs that I'm willing to tune to do this is I'm
willing to mess with the initializations
at a per-layer basis.
I'm willing to mess with the learning
rates on a per-parameter basis as well.
And then I'm sometimes willing to scale up or down things
like residual connections based on the size of my model.
So that's the game that I'd like to play.
And how well does it work in practice?
There's been several papers that have studied these fairly
extensively.
Cerebras，一家真正的芯片公司，也
拥有一个语言模型训练部门
由Hestness运营，他因缩放定律论文而闻名。
我觉得他们做的事情很有趣，因为他们
现在正在撰写大量关于语言模型的muP缩放的论文
并且他们几年前就有了Cerebras GPT，
当时他们使用通常的
Chinchilla配方训练0.1到13b模型，但也包括muP变体，
他们用它来尝试更有效地
调优超参数。
我认为其中一个好处是，他们发现如果使用muP参数化，
那么他们的缩放定律拟合通常更稳定。
他们预测的muP趋势几乎完全准确
对于他们的实际模型。
而我认为他们的非muP模型
在损失预测方面波动要大得多
他们所拥有的。
所以他们的主张是，OK。
MuP可能是一个非常好的想法。
所以这在大规模上得到了验证。
你看到了MiniCPM等。
许多人用muP变体训练了模型。
所以我也可以谈论很多关于训练或例子
用muP训练的模型。
但我认为也许对我来说更有趣的事情
现在要做的是实际上谈论
muP的概念基础和数学。
如果你对此感兴趣，
并且你想读一篇相对易懂的论文，
我会推荐这一篇。
这是我认为对我来说最清晰的论文。
有几篇论文。
Greg Yang，他开始了这个研究项目，
有一系列论文，我将称之为张量程序。
我觉得它们有些难以理解。
Jeremy Bernstein，他也参与了muon相关的工作，
写了这篇不错的——不是回顾论文，像是一篇综述
论文，把它放进了不同的框架中，我认为
这非常易懂。
And there are several others by physicists
that are also interesting in terms of explaining what muP is.
The Cerebras people actually do a bit of that as well.
But anyway, returning to this paper, the core idea of muP
is based off of two kind of assertions.
And this is a very physicist way of thinking about this.
So if I make my network big-- let's
say I'm only changing the width for now.
I'm making the width of my network big.
I'm going to assert two invariants that should
hold as I do the scaling limit.
First of all, the activations at initialization--
so if I initialize my model, and I put in some random data,
the activations should remain the same size roughly
as a function of the network.
So if they blow up with the network size,
or they shrink to 0 with the network size,
I have chosen a wrong parameterization.
And that makes sense.
My activation should be roughly the same scale, regardless
of the size of my network.
Now, after one gradient step, the change in my activation
should be O of 1.
So this is what people call feature learning.
So feature learning means if I take a gradient step, things
in my network change a significant amount
and that this amount should be a fixed function
of the width of the network.
In case some of you are theorists,
you might be familiar with neural tangent kernels.
Neural tangent kernels would have a very different behavior.
Those would be the kinds of things
where the change in activations actually
vanish as a function of the network width.
And you don't want that, because you do want the network
to change and learn features and do things even
in the limit of your big neural networks.
So these two are the invariants.
They make sense.
They're basically saying, activations and the change
in the activations should remain roughly similar
as a function of the width of the network.
And then note that I'm going to sometimes
go back and forth between individual activations, which
is this.
And then the norm, which--
if each activation is roughly O of 1,
the norm of the whole vector of activation
should be square root of the number
of hidden units in that layer.
OK, so that's the main thing.
Now, the thing about muP is it's interesting
because it starts with this very simple and palatable set
of assumptions.
You might all agree that this is a reasonable thing to do.
And then we're going to make a number
of additional strong assumptions.
But then, in the end, we're going
to get a very simple set of scaling
rules that drop out of this.
So remember, what we want to do is
we want to make sure that the activation is
at init are roughly unit.
So what do we do?
Well, if we have a simple deep linear network,
and we initialize all of our weights
as a sigma squared scaled Gaussian,
then what is going to be the spectral norm of this matrix?
Well, you can write that down.
I'm not going to ask you to verify that,
but that's standard matrix concentration
arguments for the operator norm of a random Gaussian matrix.
And then now note that in certain regimes where
the fan-out is, I think, not much bigger than the fan-in,
you're going to get that the output of the layer
is similar to the product of the input of the layer
times the operator norm.
This is always an upper bound, but this approximate in certain high-dimensional regimes.
Now, if this is true, now what can we do?
Well, we can solve for sigma to try
to keep our activations the same across all the layers
and across all the width.
So imagine that at layer L minus 1,
I have square root of L minus 1 activation.
And this is, remember, consistent with this notation
that, at least for this whole vector,
I should have square root of n of L.
So this is our base case for induction.
And then our inductive case says, well,
remember that I have this operator norm at layer
L, which is this function of the fan in and the fan out.
And so this is going to be equal to this
if I pick a particular sigma.
So let's say this is the ansatz.
I'm going to assume that this is the answer,
and then we'll see what happens to the induction.
If I pick this as a hypothesis, and I plug this into the sigma,
notice that I get that the ratio of the operator norm
is this, the ratio of the fan out
over the-- sorry, square root of the fan-out over the square root
of the fan-in.
And then I plug this back in here.
And then I'm going to get that the norm of the output
is going to be equal to the square root of the number
of units in my layer plus some lower-order terms
that I'm not going to bother to keep track of.
So where this sigma came out of--
I mean, this is drawing it out of a hat.
But we can verify that if I plug this noise initialization
into my formula, then, essentially, at every layer,
the size of my activations is roughly
equal to the square root of the number of hidden
units at that layer.
There are some assumptions made here,
like this approximate equals.
But this is mostly a legitimate set of assumptions.
So condition A1 is pretty simple.
Condition A2 is a little bit hairier, to be honest.
So really, we need to deal with the updates now.
And I'm only going to consider the case of a single example
in a batch for SGD for linear neural networks, so
deep linear network.
So what is this going to look like?
Well, the change in my weights for a particular layer L--
if you think about how this is going to behave,
it's going to be a rank 1 update between my gradient for the loss
and the activations.
This is true just because of the behavior of the backwards.
The forwards is a rank 1 multiplication.
The backwards is going to be a rank 1 outer product.
So now this is the change in the weights.
And now what is the change in the activations at that layer?
Well, the change in the activations--
I just take h equals W times h l minus 1, and I expand this out.
And I expand this out into this formula.
This is going to be exactly the change
in the activation at layer L.
And it's going to have two terms, one
that is the direct term from changes in the activation at L
minus 1 and the cross term in some sense of what happens
because my weights have changed, not
just because the activations of the previous layer have changed.
So there's two terms to this update.
And so this is the change in the activation at layer L.
And now what I'm going to do is I'm
going to look through each of these three terms.
I want each of these three terms to have
the same order of magnitude, and I want that order of magnitude
to be square root of n of L. Why is that?
Remember that, if I go back two slides,
the condition that I want for A2 is that after one gradient step,
the change in activation should be O of 1 or omega of 1.
And so if I want that to be true,
then the norm of that layer should be square root of nl.
And so to do that, what I want is for each of these three terms
to have that order of magnitude.
And if that's true, and there's no cancelations,
then this is going to be the right order of magnitude.
You can see the sketchy pieces adding up.
We're assuming things like no cancelations and so on,
but this is giving us some interesting ways
of thinking about the magnitude of each of these objects.
So at this point, the right way to think about this is not like, OK, Tatsu is sitting here
doing rigorous mathematics.
What I am doing here is I'm basically
keeping track of all the orders of magnitude of all the terms.
And I am saying that, given our assumptions,
how big should these roughly be?
It's physicist's math.
No offense to physicists.
This was developed by physicists in this way.
OK, so now really-- sorry, go back one slide just
to make all this clear.
So the first term, this comes by almost assumption.
It's the inductive assumption.
We assume that delta h of l minus 1
has the right order of magnitude.
So this comes for free.
These other two terms-- these are trickier.
We have these terms that multiply
the change in my weights in operator norm times
square root of L minus 1.
And so because these two are the order of magnitude
of both of these terms, we know how big
this delta L needs to be.
We can solve for this because we know
that this left-hand side needs to be square root L.
And then we have this term, so we solve for this operator norm.
And that's exactly this quantity.
So this is going to be the goal for the next slide.
I want to try to figure out what kinds of learning rates
are going to give me an update that's roughly scaled
as the square root of the fan-out over the square root
of the fan-in.
So that's the goal.
As I said, after I pick a learning rate,
this should roughly be true.
So how can we do that?
Well, we're going to make yet another assumption.
And this is probably the least palatable of the assumptions,
In my opinion, which is that we're
going to assume that the loss update is
going to be scaled by unit.
In other words, we're going to assume
that our model is actually making
some appreciable, nontrivial progress as a function of scale
and that that's roughly similar.
Not quite sure that's palatable to me,
but that is yet another assumption.
So we throw that down.
But now the point of this assumption
is that if this is true, the rest of the math
works out quite cleanly, because the change in the loss
is the product of my gradient plus
how much my weights changed.
This is Taylor approximation.
And then because this is rank 1, I
can rewrite this thing as a Frobenius norm
and as an operator norm.
And so this right-hand side now allows us to get what we want.
This is O of 1.
This term we want to be square root n over square root l
minus 1.
That's this term on the right here.
And then finally, I have this gradient of L term.
And this is going to be square root of NL
minus 1 over square root nl.
And then so now what eta do I need?
Well, the eta that I need is going
to be solving for this quantity, which
is the ratio of these two guys, which is nl over nl minus 1.
So we made this one assumption that the left-hand side of this O of 1.
And then we've solved for all the quantities,
and we've ended up with a fan-out over fan-in ratio
for a learning rate for a layer.
One side note that I'll make is that for Adam,
because of the changes in some of this, you're going to get a 1
over nl minus 1 scaling, which I'll mention here.
So I've walked through a bunch of hopefully intuitive-looking
scaling arguments for various components.
But in the end, maybe you are interested in,
what does this mean?
What does this do for me?
What this means is that we're going
to change how we set our initializations
and learning rates a little bit.
So our initialization is going to look like—so for muP,
the blue box is what we do.
Our initialization is going to be
1 over square root nl minus 1 times a component that
is 1 over the square root fanout over fanin.
So if this is 1, then this is equivalent
to the usual initialization.
This is the standard parameterization.
But if this ratio is not smaller than 1,
then you get basically something different.
You get something that's closer to the square root
fanout over fanin.
The learning rate normally you would
set to be a constant as a function of your model size,
but you would want to set this to the ratio of fanout
and fanin.
And maybe more interestingly, for Adam, this whole thing
is a little bit more different.
I'm not going to even touch the derivation for that, where
you drop this 1 over nl term, and you get 1
over the fanin as the layer specific learning rate.
And so basically, layers that have big fanins for Adam
get smaller learning rates.
It allows you to have these layer-adaptive learning rates
that are quite interesting.
So that was the derivation of muP.
I went through a lot of details.
I do want to maybe talk about what
the high-level point of that was.
And the high-level point of that is, muP
as an argument is very interesting.
Not only is there actual useful stuff.
The way in which you get to the algorithm
is itself interesting because it's this very different kind
of math in which you're saying, OK,
I'm going to take a scaling limit of my network.
And then I assert some invariance about my network,
and then I'm going to make additional assumptions.
And then I'm going to try to figure out
what the constraints on my hyperparameters are.
And the constraints essentially give you
certain kinds of scaling limits on your hyperparameters as well.
So this is a general principle for coming up
with different kinds of algorithms or hyperparameter
scalings, I think, which are probably
very different than what you're used to in CS or ML training.
OK, those are the muP derivation.
I want to close out on the muP part with just
a few empirical things.
There's an interesting paper by an independent researcher
on basically stress testing muP in lots of different ways.
And muP can be thought of as a procedure
for tuning hyperparameters.
And so depending on how you do things,
Adam is going to have a certain learning
rate as a function of different components of the network.
So you have an embedding parameter, attention parameters,
input/output MLPs or softmax linears.
All of those are going to have different kinds
of scalings under muP, as well as not muP scaling rules.
And the interesting thing here is that particular paper
replicated a bunch of the muP results
for language models trained at different scales.
And maybe unsurprisingly, he found almost the headline result
from MiniCPM and others, which is
that if you get the muP right, and you're only scaling with,
in this case, in a very controlled way,
you get exactly the learning rate optimality
invariance that baseline muP--
or just looking at a variant of muP that
tracks projection biases for attention, both of those
transfer very nicely.
But then you might ask, basically,
there's a lot of things in the real world
that muP does not handle.
Technically, SwiGLU does not fit into muP,
neither does initialize variations, initialization
or RMS norm.
Or if you really mess with your optimizer,
that will mess that up, too.
And so you might ask, like, which
of these things that are not allowed by the theory
really break muP?
And actually, for the most part, these mostly work with muP.
But some of the things that don't work
is if you learn the gain term in RMS norm,
this turns out to break muP.
Although, these can be removed in many cases
without necessarily hurting you, and so maybe
it's not such a bad idea.
But this does seem to break muP.
It also seems to break if you use more exotic optimizers
like Lion, which basically rely on the sign of the gradient.
And sign gradient is like a spiritually
similar to muon and other ideas.
And so there might be other interesting things
that break with muP as well.
Finally, the thing that seems most concerning
is that if you do large decoupled weight decay,
you end up with significant muP failure.
So this is maybe the one stress test that it does fail.
But to close out this final section, you might, in the end,
ask, like, is muP useful?
And if you really want to stabilize your learning rates,
it is actually pretty useful.
There's a lot of experiments of this form, where
if you increase the width, your optimal learning rate shifts
very predictably, but very greatly as a function of scale.
Whereas, with muP it doesn't.
And so it's one of the many tools in the toolkit
to try to control hyperparameter drift as a function of scale.
I think it's an interesting open area of research.
It's not really done and dusted, and this the one right thing to do.
But there's a lot of promise in the muP-style initialization
program.
There's also a lot of promise in just fitting scaling laws
as well.
So the final thing I want to close with, scaling in the wild
is very tricky.
As I mentioned in one of my replies.
I think the initial presentation of scaling laws
makes it sound like a science.
It's like, yes, draw this line, do these procedures,
and you will know, for sure, what will happen at scale.
But I think, in reality, it's a lot more messy and a lot more
unknown than that.
There are lots of things that people
do use in practice scaling laws for,
like picking architectures, picking optimizers, picking
hyperparameters.
All of these things are things that people
do with scaling laws, but there is really an art to it
in the sense of, you don't really
if it's truly going to extrapolate forever.
You want to do reasonable things to maximize
the chances of success.
And so there's lots of solutions that people have.
You can use muP.
You can search for the optimal learning rate in all
of these other kinds of things.
And these are ways of controlling hyperparameter drift.
But there's no silver bullet yet.
Maybe next year, there will be a module
that's like, we solved it, but not quite yet.
Great. Thanks a lot.
I can take questions afterwards.